Guide to the Miriam Seidman Blaukopf nee Blasenstein collection, 1914-1978.
Blaukopf, Miriam Seidman nee Blasenstein papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Miriam Seidman Blaukopf nee Blasenstein collection, 1914-1978.
6916
1 box.
Correspondence, photographs, tape recordings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, photographs, tape recordings and other material regarding Polish holocaust survivors.
Miriam Seidman Blaukopf survived four years in hiding from the Nazis in German-occupied Poland. Her granddaughter, Nina Peterson, interviewed her and compiled other information about her.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Reparations and other personal correspondence, Leo and Miriam Blaukopf, 1957-1968. Original correspondence, notes, and translations, including letters from family and friends, 1937-62, letters from Isaac Miller to Miriam, 1914-1930; notes and maps by Nina Peterson; letters from Miriam to America, 1945-46 (3 letters translated by Nina Peterson); translations of selected notes and communications by Murray Sachs and Nina Peterson. Passports, identification paper, and immigration papers for Leo Blaukopf, Miriam Blaukopf, and Nina Peterson; newspaper articles from German and Austrian papers (and "California Farmer" article on Adolph Miller, 1954). Three unpublished manuscripts written by Miriam Seidman Blaukopf include biography beginning with Krystallnacht in 1938 when she was still in Vienna, continuing with her return to Poland and ending with her liberation and trek to relocation authorities in Rome in 1945; earlier years - childhood and marriage; and brief summary manuscript. Manuscript "Ferramonti di Tarsi," by Nina Wekeler, typewritten in German, 1941, about the internment camp in Italy where Leo Blaukopf was sent. Also, photographs; tape recordings of interviews with Miriam by Nina Peterson, with CD copies.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Blasenstein family.; Blaukopf family.; Blaukopf, Leo.; Blaukopf, Miriam Seidman.; Peterson, Nina.; Sachs, Murray.; Seidman family.; Ferramonti (Concentration camp)
Subjects:
Holocaust survivors.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945)--Personal narratives.; Concentration camps--Italy--Calabria.; Emigration and immigration.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Biographical information, family tree, timeline, reel-to-reel tape/CD guide, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Leo and Miriam Blaukopf correspondence and reparations, 1954 - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Leo and Miriam Blaukopf correspondence and reparations, 1966 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Miriam Blaukopf pensions, 1965 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Miriam Blaukopf correspondence, 1957 - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Kurt and Hilde Blaukopf correspondence, 1945 - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Includes 4 photographs
- Correspondence from friends and family, 1937 - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence from Isaac(IJ) Miller to Miriam Blaukopf, 1914 - 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes 1 photograph, one translation by Murray Sachs
- Necha (Nina) Peterson, notes and maps, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence from Miriam Blaukopf to America, 1945 - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes translations of three letters by Necha(Nina) Peterson
- Correspondence, notes and translations, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Translations of selected notes and correspondence by Murray Sachs and Necha(Nina) Peterson
- Leo Blaukopf passports, identification transit papers, birth record, 1887 - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Newspaper articles, booklet, 1907 - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Includes picture of Buczacz, Poland community members, Einstein Memorial article, booklet with photographs of Bergen-Belsen camp and memorial for unknown Jewish martyrs, articles from Zeitspiegel Austrian Weekly, Jung Osterreich, Aufbau and California Farmer
- Immigration papers, marriage certificate, 1936 - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Includes copy of passport for Necha(Nina) Peterson, marriage certificate and naturalization papers for Leo Blaukopf and Miriam Seitman
- Manuscripts, handwritten in Yiddish by Miriam Blaukopf, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Manuscript A - begins with Krystallnacht in 1938 when Miriam Blaukopf was still living in Vienna. It continues with her return to Poland and ends with her liberation and trek through several countries to relocation authorities in Rome in 1945. Manuscript B - childhood and marriage. Manuscript C - brief summary of the first two manuscripts.
- Ferramonti[di Tarsi] by Nina Wekeler, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photographs, ca. 1906 - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Some originals, some photocopies. Includes master list and approximate dates.
- Reel-to-reel tape - Necha(Nina) Peterson interviews with Mariam Blaukopf in Yiddish. Interview 1 - childhood Kolanki, Interview 12 - Bindergasse, 18-20 years., n.d.; tr-9915 (Box 1)
- Reel-to-reel tape - Necha(Nina) Peterson interviews with Mariam Blaukopf in Yiddish. Interview 2 - Horodenka, marriage, family, Kotikovka, pre-WWI. Interview 11 - Tlusty, Bindergasse, Horodenka., n.d.; tr-9916 (Box 1)
- Reel-to-reel tape - Necha(Nina) Peterson interviews with Mariam Blaukopf in Yiddish. Interview 3 - WWI, Vienna, school. Interview 10 - German translation, Avrom hospital, Beile, Horodenka, Kommandante, 1939 - 1940, Gestapo, December 4, 1940., n.d.; tr-9917 (Box 1)
- Reel-to-reel tape - Necha(Nina) Peterson interviews with Mariam Blaukopf in Yiddish. Interview 4 - Vienna, Anschloss, 18 years Wohlmutstrasse, 28 years Adoplh comes to Horodenka. Interview 9 - German translation, Horodenka, Beile., n.d.; tr-9918 (Box 1)
- Reel-to-reel tape - Necha(Nina) Peterson interviews with Mariam Blaukopf in Yiddish. Interview 5 - Return to Poland from Vienna, Berlin, Beuten, Katowicz, Tandelmarktgasse, Austria, Horodenka, November 1938. Interview 8 - German Translation, Nazi invasion of Horodenka 1939., n.d.; tr-9919 (Box 1)
- Reel-to-reel tape - Necha(Nina) Peterson interviews with Mariam Blaukopf in Yiddish. Interview 6 - Vienna 1938, Bindergasse, Horodenka. Interview 7 - Vienna, German translation., n.d.; tr-9920 (Box 1)
- Reel-to-reel tape - Necha(Nina) Peterson interviews with Mariam Blaukopf in Yiddish. Interview 13 - Father in hospital, Horodenka, Kolanki, Dr. Karpf. Interview 14 - Kolanki, end of story, America., n.d.; tr-9921 (Box 1)
- Reel-to-reel tape - Necha(Nina) Peterson interviews with Mariam Blaukopf in Yiddish. Interview 15 - Tluste, Czortkov, back to Horodenka, Dniester river, Feige's children, Bucharest. Interview 16 - Horodenka, Chernovitz, Bucharest,Hungary, Mamarocz-Szigeth, Graz., n.d.; tr-9922 (Box 1)
- CD of tape interviews 1,2,3,4,5., n.d.; CD-2012 (Box 1)
- CD of tape interviews 6, 13 15., n.d.; CD-2013 (Box 1)
- CD of tape interviews 7,8,9,10,11., n.d.; CD-2014 (Box 1)
- CD of tape interviews 12, 14,16., n.d.; CD-2015 (Box 1)
- CD of three tape interviews - 4,6,12. Filtered by a recording technician., n.d.; CD-2016 (Box 1)